<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The patterne of all pious prayer, and the epitomie of all Christian Catholique beliefe being a patheticall and paraphrastical meeter vpon the Pater Noster, Ave Maria, and Credo in Deum, &amp;c. : together with a divine dittie made vpon St. Patricks Day last past in honour of the Christian crosse, with wholsome preparatives for death and judgment : also a short panigyre on Mary-land in America.</title>
            <author>Mayerne, Patrick.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07362</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17746</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1631</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">20241199</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 20241199</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23901</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07362)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23901)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1710:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The patterne of all pious prayer, and the epitomie of all Christian Catholique beliefe being a patheticall and paraphrastical meeter vpon the Pater Noster, Ave Maria, and Credo in Deum, &amp;c. : together with a divine dittie made vpon St. Patricks Day last past in honour of the Christian crosse, with wholsome preparatives for death and judgment : also a short panigyre on Mary-land in America.</title>
                  <author>Mayerne, Patrick.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[47] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Dovvay :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXXXVI [1636]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>"His name in anagram hear's: Marke Prayer in't."--P. [7].</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Mayerne by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>"Superiorum permissu."</note>
                  <note>Signatures: a-c⁸.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: recto of signature a1 and panegyric lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayer --  Catholic Church.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Catholic authors.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="frontispiece">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:1"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <q>COR CHARTE APPENSAM ROSAM VICE CERNE SIGILLI SPRETA MORE TVI SALVS ID EGIT AMOR</q>
                        <p>IHS</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:1"/>
                  <p>THE PATTERNE OF ALL PIOVS PRAYER, AND The epitomie of all Chriſtian Catholique Beliefe.</p>
                  <p>Being a Patheticall and Paraphraſticall meeter vpon the <hi>Pater Noſter, Ave Maria,</hi> and <hi>Credo in Deum, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Together with a divine Dittie made vpon S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Patricks</hi> Day laſt paſt in honour of the Chriſtian <hi>Croſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>WITH Wholſome preparatives for Death and Judgment</p>
                  <p>ALSO, A ſhort Panigyre on MARY-<hi>Land</hi> in <hi>America.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AT DOVVAY, Superiorum Permiſſu, MDCXXXVI.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="deciation">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:2"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND TRVLY RELIGIOVS LADY, THE LADY Vizcounteſſe BALTEMORI, &amp;c.</head>
                  <lg n="1">
                     <head>1</head>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>Ouchſafe Religious Lady to make choyce</l>
                     <l>('Mongſt All your Vertues) of humilitie,</l>
                     <l>That your poore Suppliant juſtly may Reioyce</l>
                     <l>In the fore-front of his Apologie:</l>
                     <l>To fruſtrate All objections by this ſhift,</l>
                     <l>An humble heart A'cepts the meaneſt guiſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="2">
                     <head>2</head>
                     <l>May you Accuſe mee of Preſumption; no</l>
                     <l>Spare that paine (Madam) 'tis Already done,</l>
                     <l>J have accus'd my Selfe: And you I know</l>
                     <l>To pardon faults Confeſt are eaſily wonne:</l>
                     <l>Let <hi>Zoylus</hi> ſnarle, let <hi>Momus</hi> looke aſquint,</l>
                     <l>Your worth will guard the Booke, And, <hi>MARKE PRAYER IN'Y.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:3"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:3"/>
                  <head>WITH THE COVRTEOVS Chriſtian Reader thus I expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulate.</head>
                  <p>COurteous Reader, ſhould I ſuffer knowne faults to paſſe without cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving pardon, I might bee juſtly accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and condemned both of Ignorance and Preſumption; which I hope thy Charity will acquit me of when thou haſt read this my reaſonable Apologie; The way to gaine Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is Confeſſion, And in this I cannot rightly excuſe but rather accuſe my ſelfe, in that aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming a taske fit for a more ſublime Intelect: I haue (peradventure) marr'd that which a better Workman might have made Admirable; yet if
<pb facs="tcp:23901:4"/>good will may ſupply want of skill, I hope wee ſhall agree well enough.</p>
                  <p>I found the Latine ſomething difficult to Rime too, eſpecially the CREED; And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore having preocupated curious Cenſures, in confeſſing my fault I hope thou wilt excuſe and connive if thou finde it any thing Defective ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in meeter or the length of the lines, there beeing ſome Articles in the CREED over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long for my intended line, And vpon neceſſity muſt paſſe without fraction where Rime may not exactly bee made, without diſtruction of reaſon. Any indifferent Reader (I truſt) will favourably paſſe over ſuch faults as cannot bee holpen: To conclude gentle Chriſtian, permit mee a little (after confeſſion of immateriall De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects) to ſay ſomething in praiſe of the Work though not of the Workman; The ſubject is
<pb facs="tcp:23901:4"/>olde, therefore it is fit to bee reverenced. The Paraphraſe is new (without Oſtentation bee it ſpoken) none having ever written in this way before, And therefore to bee loved for its raritie.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>VALE.</salute>
                  </closer>
                  <byline>Hee who compoſed what is heere in print, <lb/> His name in Anagram hear's: <hi>Marke Prayer in't.</hi>
                  </byline>
               </div>
               <div type="encomium">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:5"/>
                  <head>Ad Authorem.</head>
                  <l>TO make the <hi>Engliſh</hi> anſwer <hi>Latine</hi> phraſe</l>
                  <l>In Meeter meete ſhewes wit that's worthy Praiſe,</l>
                  <l>But where the Subiects Godly; Lines exceede,</l>
                  <l>All beſt Wits Apprehenſion there indeede,</l>
                  <l>More be thy <hi>Piety,</hi> for ſuch eſſayes,</l>
                  <l>Prayſ'd then thy Wit to frame ſuch Heavenly layes.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>I. P.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:5"/>
                  <head>A PARAPHRASTICALL MEETER VPON PATER NOSTER.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>CHarity</hi>'s the guift of guifts, if we have loſt her</l>
                  <l>Who can reſtore her to's but — <hi>Pater noſter:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For hee in all diſtreſſe our onely weale is</l>
                  <l>And none but thou alone — <hi>Qui es in Coelis:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our ſoules bedrencht in ſinne with grace renew'em</l>
                  <l>For which — <hi>Sanctificetur nomen tuum:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thoſe who doe erre reduce, and true light ſhew'em</l>
                  <l>Make haſt O Lord, — <hi>Ad veniat regnum tuum:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To whom the Heavenly Quier ſings <hi>Alleluia</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>'Tis fit wee ſay; — <hi>Fiat voluntas tua:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Wee wiſh the ſame either in Ioy or Sorrow</l>
                  <l>'Tis due — <hi>Sicut in Coelo &amp; in terra:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As thou mad'ſt all of nought thy power mainteyn'm</l>
                  <l>With bounty — <hi>Panem noſtrum Quotidianum:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:6"/>
                  <l>And every day to ſhew what due wee Owe thee</l>
                  <l>Wee earneſtly doe begge — <hi>Da nobis hodic:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>'Tis fit wee ſhould when wee doe merit moſt; pray</l>
                  <l>Deare Lord — <hi>Et dimitte nobis debita noſtra:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>On this Condition elſe our prayer all loſt is, —</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sicut &amp; nos dimittimus debitoribus noſtris:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Though wee offend in wrath doe not rebuke vs,</l>
                  <l>O bee propitious — <hi>Et ne nos in ducas:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When by my ſelfe in private I alone am</l>
                  <l>Permit mee not <hi>Iheſu:</hi> — <hi>Jn tentaetionem:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In Senſuality let vs not wallow,</l>
                  <l>Nor fall from thee — <hi>Sed libera nos a malo:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This in thy name <hi>Iheſu</hi> wee aske, And when</l>
                  <l>All's done, wee pray that thou mayſt ſay — <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Ave Maria.</head>
                  <l>VVHo ever hopes for helpe from our <hi>Meſſia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Muſt to his mother ſay — <hi>Ave Maria:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:6"/>
                  <l>To thy Sonnes Court being ſent for by <hi>Subpaena,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Wee vſe thy Prayer, for thou art <hi>Gratia plena:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thoſe Prayers none can miſſe that dayly ſeeke 'em;</l>
                  <l>How can wee fayle, knowing that <hi>Dominus tecum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The holy Angell <hi>Gabriels</hi> words were very thus,</l>
                  <l>To thee <hi>Benedicta tu in Mulieribus:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Wee are perſwaded that thou canſt protect vs,</l>
                  <l>For thou art high in power <hi>Et benedictus:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Wherefore by thee ſweete Mediatrix ſue I</l>
                  <l>Vnto that bleſſed, <hi>Fructus ventris tui:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sicke ſoules, Alas, whom can w'expect to caſe vs,</l>
                  <l>But that Maide, Mothers Sonne, <hi>Emanuell-Iheſus:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To get admittance at this Gate, the nigh way</l>
                  <l>Is by thy powerfull ayde <hi>Sancta Maria:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Virgin of Virgins, in this caſe to thee I</l>
                  <l>Addreſſe my ſelfe as vnto <hi>Mater Dei:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>All ſinnefull Soules, that for miſdeeds are ſorry thus</l>
                  <l>Doe ſay, <hi>Ora pro nobis Peccatoribus:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And let vs leaſt our part in Heaven bee loſt, pray</l>
                  <l>O helpe <hi>Nunc et in hora, Mortis noſtra:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:7"/>
                  <l>Sweete Lady wee intreate thee now and then,</l>
                  <l>To pray thy Sonne (our Lord) to ſay, <hi>Amen,</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Credo in Deum, &amp;c.</head>
                  <l>IVdg'd at the high Tribunall what ſhall wee doe,</l>
                  <l>If each in Tongue and Heart, cannot ſay <hi>Credo:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When ſtorms ariſe, he with his breath can ſcatter 'em</l>
                  <l>Therefore I doe confide <hi>In deum Patrem:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What ere men plot 'gainſt him he can prevent 'em</l>
                  <l>Whoſe onely Epithet's, <hi>Ommiptent em:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Wee nothing have but what from him wee borrow,</l>
                  <l>For hee is, <hi>Creatorem Coeli, et Terrae:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He made all things, and to mans vſe he bleſt 'em</l>
                  <l>I beleeve in him: <hi>Et in Iheſum Chriſtum:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sweeter to mee then Honey, or th'honey Combe</l>
                  <l>Is he whom God calls, <hi>Filium ejus vnicum:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He to Redeeme vs, when our Soules were loſt came,</l>
                  <l>Therefore wee rightly call him, <hi>Dominum-noſtrum:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:7"/>
                  <l>Wee cannot Retribute ſufficient thankes to</l>
                  <l>Him, <hi>Qui conceptus eſt de ſpiritu Sancto:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Prophets and the Sybels wrote at large when he</l>
                  <l>Should come to be, <hi>Natus ex Maria Virgine:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our loving Lord, tendred our wretched State ſo</l>
                  <l>That hee, <hi>Paſsus ſub Pontio Pilato:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And meekely hee for Man that doth inſult thus</l>
                  <l>Was <hi>Crucifixus Mortuus et Sepultus:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And that he Victory over Hell might winne for vs,</l>
                  <l>Our bleſt Redeemer, <hi>Decendit ad inferos:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To give poſſeſſion of the Heauenly Court to vs,</l>
                  <l>Hee <hi>tertia die reſurrexit a Mortuis:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>All to confirme being of our wellfare Zealous,</l>
                  <l>Hee crown'd with tryumph, <hi>Aſcendit ad Caelos:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In ſplendant Glory that moſt Excellent is,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sedet ad dextram Dei patris Omnipotentis:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>At th'end o'th World, (as verity doth report to us</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Inde ventarus judicare vivos et mortuous:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>God as his Elect Children all hath ranckt 'em,</l>
                  <l>Who in their Hearts ſay, <hi>Credo in Spirit um ſanctum:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:8"/>
                  <l>Yet woe is me (alas) I in meere Folly am,</l>
                  <l>Vnleſſe I beleeve — <hi>Sanctam Eccleſiam Catholicam:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who takes the name of Catholique vpon him,</l>
                  <l>Alſo beleeves <hi>Sanctorum Communionem:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In this true Church, I that a Sinner fore am;</l>
                  <l>May finde — <hi>Remiſſionem peccatorum:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And all the faithfull ſhal have this grace ſhewen 'em</l>
                  <l>As they beleeve <hi>carnis Reſurrectionem.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Let Chriſtians looke to't this doth moſt concerne 'em</l>
                  <l>Which is the Crowne of all <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>itam eternam:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Beleeve one God, beleeve his Church, and then,</l>
                  <l>Thou maiſt enjoy Chriſt promiſes, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:8"/>
                  <head>A DIVINE DITTIE, Made in <hi>Honor</hi> of the <hi>Crimſon Croſſe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>To bee Sung by them who pleaſe. To the tune of, <hi>From the faire</hi> Lavinian Shore, &amp;c.</opener>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:9"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>YOu who take delight to know</l>
                     <l>Things that were done long agoe,</l>
                     <l>By our Auncient Predeceſſors,</l>
                     <l>And their Catholicke Succeſſors.</l>
                     <l>Lend your attention</l>
                     <l>Let noe Fancies toſſe,</l>
                     <l>Your mindes a ſtray</l>
                     <l>But regard what I ſay</l>
                     <l>For I meane to diſplay,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Honor of the</hi> Crimſon <hi>Croſſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He or ſhe, who hath not bin</l>
                     <l>(In the Font that cleanſeth ſinne)</l>
                     <l>Marked with this ſacred ſigne</l>
                     <l>Give me leave though noe Divine,</l>
                     <l>To make a queſtion.</l>
                     <l>(Though ſome a ſtrange gloſſe</l>
                     <l>Doe ſet on the text)</l>
                     <l>Whether they be well fixt</l>
                     <l>In this world, for the next;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sith Chriſtians are knowne by th' Croſſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:9"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Our bleſt Lord to give vs breath</l>
                     <l>And Redeeme our Soules from Death,</l>
                     <l>On a <hi>Croſſe</hi> was Crucified</l>
                     <l>At that time he Sanctified,</l>
                     <l>This Badge of Honor,</l>
                     <l>When with his lives loſſe,</l>
                     <l>After much p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ine</l>
                     <l>While his bloud like to Raine,</l>
                     <l>From his wounds ſlowed amaine,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hee made it a</hi> Crimſon <hi>Croſſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>All the Chriſtians Primative</l>
                     <l>To advance the Croſſe did ſtrive,</l>
                     <l>Glorious <hi>Martyres</hi> Valiantly</l>
                     <l>Death and Torments did defie.</l>
                     <l>Vnder this Enſigne</l>
                     <l>Deeming but droſſe,</l>
                     <l>All things beſide</l>
                     <l>When for CHRIST Crucified</l>
                     <l>They couragiouſly Dyed,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To Honour the</hi> Crimſon <hi>Croſſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:10"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Biſhops and Confeſſors Grave,</l>
                     <l>This Coeleſtiall Banner have,</l>
                     <l>Fixt in Countryes, Salvage and Rude,</l>
                     <l>To CHRISTS <hi>Croſſe</hi> they have ſubdued,</l>
                     <l>Barbarous Nations</l>
                     <l>From their errours groſſe,</l>
                     <l>To CHRISTIAN Faith</l>
                     <l>As Antiquity ſaveth</l>
                     <l>Both in Life, and Death,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>They Honor'd the</hi> Crimſon <hi>Croſſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Once 'twas <hi>Englands</hi> primeſt Honor</l>
                     <l>Chiefely cald Saint <hi>Georges</hi> Banner,</l>
                     <l>Still the tree wee all retaine</l>
                     <l>Though the fruit on't moſt diſdaine.</l>
                     <l>But Ancient Cuſtomes,</l>
                     <l>Preſerved from loſſe</l>
                     <l>Though juſt in ſight</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Heraldryes</hi> Right</l>
                     <l>Wee on Land, and Sea ſight,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To Honor the</hi> Crimſon <hi>Croſſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:10"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>It the Divell doth affright,</l>
                     <l>He dares not abide in ſight</l>
                     <l>Where this holy ſigne is made</l>
                     <l>Wherefore it may well be ſaid,</l>
                     <l>That he and the Puritan</l>
                     <l>With his falſe gloſſe,</l>
                     <l>Are neere of kinne</l>
                     <l>Neither dares enter in</l>
                     <l>If I once doe begin</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To arme my ſelfe with the Croſſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Bleſt St. <hi>Patricke</hi> who 'at th' firſt</l>
                     <l>(As Apoſtle) <hi>Ireland</hi> nurſt</l>
                     <l>In the Faith Apoſtolique</l>
                     <l>Scoft by every Heretique,</l>
                     <l>He ſo Devoutly</l>
                     <l>Did Vertue engroſſe,</l>
                     <l>That in ſhort time</l>
                     <l>Hee converted that Clime</l>
                     <l>To CHRISTS Faith then in Prime</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And Honor'd the</hi> Crimſon <hi>Croſſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:11"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ireland</hi> then was ſore oppreſt</l>
                     <l>With foule things that did infeſt</l>
                     <l>And the People ſore annoy</l>
                     <l>Which St. <hi>Patrick</hi> did deſtroy,</l>
                     <l>Snakes, Toades, and Adders,</l>
                     <l>O gainefull loſſe,</l>
                     <l>All by his Prayer</l>
                     <l>Quite Banniſhed were</l>
                     <l>Never more to come there</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>This Honors the</hi> Crimſon <hi>Croſſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To his Honor and the Chutch,</l>
                     <l>Every ſeaventeenth day of <hi>March</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iriſh</hi> men doe farre, and neare,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Crimſen Croſſes</hi> that day weare</l>
                     <l>Then let true CHRITIANS</l>
                     <l>Eſteeme Wealth as droſſe,</l>
                     <l>And in all wants</l>
                     <l>Let vs move our Complaints</l>
                     <l>Vnto CHRIST by his Saints</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And Honour the</hi> Crimſon <hi>Croſſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>AMEN,</closer>
                  <trailer>
                     <hi>Finis.</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23901:11"/>
                     <figure>
                        <q>COR CHARTE APPENSAM ROSAM VICE CERNE SIGILLI SPRETA MORE TVI SALVS ID EGIT AMOR</q>
                        <p>IHS</p>
                     </figure>
                  </trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:12"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>WHOLSOME PREPARATIVES FOR DEATH AND IVDGEMENT: VERY FIT TO BEE APPLYED TO the neceſſitie of every true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique CHRISTIAN at all times; But more eſpecially in this preſent time of Mortality by the Plague of Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence occaſioned.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>Statutum eſt hominibus ſemel mori: Poſt hoc autem Judicium.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Hebr. 9.27.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>Superiorum Permiſſu, MDCXXXVI.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:13"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:13"/>
                  <head>TO THE CHARITABLE READER.</head>
                  <p>GReat cauſe I had (Chriſtian Reader) to invite thee by this Epiſtle (Charitable,) for this poore Babe of my braine begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in charity, deſires to have charitable nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, charitable Cenſure, and chiefely Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble acceptation; For the tender weakeling by reaſon of its Parents weakneſſe, (ſhould it bee rigidly dealt withall) would even periſh in the very blaſt of an over-curious or faſtidious ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict; Therefore let Charity cover what indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion
<pb facs="tcp:23901:14"/>hath left naked, and let a loving heart excuſe Defects of Art; What I have heere publiſhed was done at the (powerfull) ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a very good Friend of mine, or elſe this rude worke had onely beene for the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans owne vſe: And as it was written to anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipate worſe employment; ſo as a Whetſtone to his devotion, It might have (and I truſt will) ſet a ſharper edge vpon the ſame, And conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently produce more keene and piercing ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Charity, Feare of GOD, Obedience to his immaculate Spouſe the Holy Catholique and Apoſtolique CHURCH; Reverence to his Saints, Zeale of his Honour, Fervor in true Religion, and in all pious and laudable Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes that a CHRISTIAN ought to practice. Among which, nothing can bee more vſefull and neceſſary at all times, And eſpecially in
<pb facs="tcp:23901:14"/>this heauy time of Mortalitie, Then the thought of DEATH and IVDGEMENT: Although it bee a Subject that hath beene written vpon by divers Angelicall quils, (To whoſe Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments I humbly proſtrate mine;) yet I know that a ſingle Penny or a halfe-penny is as good ſilver and as Currant coyne as a Shilling: To conclude, if any Fruit ſpring from this ſimple Seed, to him bee the honor who firſt inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</p>
                  <closer>AMEN.</closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:15"/>
                  <byline>Hee who compoſed what is heere in print, His name in Anagram hear's: <hi>Marke Prayer in't,</hi>
                  </byline>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:23901:15"/>
                     <head>WHOLSOME PREPARATIVES FOR DEATH AND IVDGMENT.</head>
                     <lg n="1">
                        <head>1.</head>
                        <l>TIs fit that every minute Night and Day,</l>
                        <l>Whilſt we draw breath in this terreſtiall frame</l>
                        <l>We ſhould reflect on the vncertaine ſtay,</l>
                        <l>Lent's here, till we returne from whence we came</l>
                        <l>This being pondered as it is moſt fit,</l>
                        <l>Much Ghoſtly comfort, wee may reape by it.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="2">
                        <head>2.</head>
                        <l>That Hee, or Shee, Young, Old, or Middle-aged,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe minde continually hereon is fixt,</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:23901:16"/>
                        <l>Shall finde Robuſtious ſtormes, ſo farre aſſwaged</l>
                        <l>(While earthly joy's with heavenly ſorrows mixt)</l>
                        <l>That with a gentle gale the Soule doth glide,</l>
                        <l>Over all Paſſions borne by Vertues tide.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="3">
                        <head>3.</head>
                        <l>No ſooner Borne, but ſubject vnto Death,</l>
                        <l>(All Mortals are indeed borne to that end)</l>
                        <l>Noe Permanent Eſtate here vnderneath,</l>
                        <l>For all muſt pay this Tribute in the End,</l>
                        <l>Or Young, or Old, wee muſt (nothing ſo ſure)</l>
                        <l>All to the Grave, no meanes can vs ſecure.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="4">
                        <head>4.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Methuſalu</hi> the Oldeſt: <hi>Salomon</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>The Wiſeſt: <hi>Sampſon</hi> ſtrongeſt man, all theſe</l>
                        <l>Though they had wiſdome, ſtrength, long life al'sone</l>
                        <l>Death would not ſet them quit paying their fees,</l>
                        <l>What ever Holy-writ hath Teſtifi'd</l>
                        <l>Of them in Life, be ſure youl'e read they Dy'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23901:16"/>
                     <lg n="5">
                        <head>5.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Creſſus</hi> his Wealth, nor <hi>Alexanders</hi> Pompe,</l>
                        <l>Nor <hi>Caeſars</hi> (rarely Imitated) Honor</l>
                        <l>Could winne on Earth Eternity; nor Campe,</l>
                        <l>Nor Court, nor City, can preſcribe a manner,</l>
                        <l>How to ſhunne this inevitable Doome,</l>
                        <l>All men muſt Dye, and then to Iudgement come.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="6">
                        <head>6.</head>
                        <l>As it is certaine that we all muſt Dye,</l>
                        <l>(Sith divine Statutes are Irrevocable,)</l>
                        <l>So that wee may't expect continually</l>
                        <l>To know the time, we Mortals are vnable;</l>
                        <l>Therfore wee ſhould from'th houre we firſt draw breath</l>
                        <l>Looke for this certaine, yet vncertaine Death.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="7">
                        <head>7.</head>
                        <l>That certaine Doctrine of <hi>Gamaliels</hi> Scholler,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Statutum eſt hominibus ſemel mori,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:23901:17"/>
                        <l>Which is the Godly's joy, the Wicked's dolour,</l>
                        <l>The Prouds confuſion, and the Humbles glory,</l>
                        <l>Is the elected theame of my Diſcourſe,</l>
                        <l>In careleſſe Chriſtians to procure remorſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="8">
                        <head>8.</head>
                        <l>Yet leaſt the onely certainty of Death,</l>
                        <l>Should not be weyed, as Iuſtice doth require</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Poſt hoc autem Judicium:</hi> After Death,</l>
                        <l>Some Iudg'd to Bliſſe, ſome to Eternall Fire:</l>
                        <l>Mee thinkes the memory of theſe two points</l>
                        <l>Should (Palſie-like) ſhake proud <hi>Belſhazers</hi> joynts.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="9">
                        <head>9.</head>
                        <l>Though it be true a Chriſtian rather ought,</l>
                        <l>For th'only love of God live Vertuouſly</l>
                        <l>If in our Hearts wee ſtill retaine this thought</l>
                        <l>O Bleſſed <hi>Iheſu,</hi> thou for Sinne didſt Dye;</l>
                        <l>And ſhall I wretch reitterate the ſame</l>
                        <l>Which cauſ'd thy cruell ſcourging Death, and ſhame.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23901:17"/>
                     <lg n="10">
                        <head>10.</head>
                        <l>But yet alas, vilde Man is ſo propence</l>
                        <l>T'ingratitude, and Epicurian ſloath</l>
                        <l>Doth ſo conſopiate and dull his ſence</l>
                        <l>Him to awake, Mercy and Iudgement both</l>
                        <l>(Being joyntly vſ'd) doe all too little ſeeme,</l>
                        <l>Of God and Goodneſſe, to winne his Eſteeme.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="11">
                        <head>11.</head>
                        <l>Indeede a tender hearted Man, or Woman,</l>
                        <l>That curiouſly in Pious Contemplation</l>
                        <l>Shall with Devotion dayly call and Summon,</l>
                        <l>Within the Breaſt to ſcan our Saviours Paſſion:</l>
                        <l>May finde moſt Charitable motives ſtill,</l>
                        <l>As ſpurs to Good, as Bridles to all Ill.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="12">
                        <head>12.</head>
                        <l>To ſuch as theſe the memory of Death,</l>
                        <l>And after Iudgement: Are both comfortable,</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:23901:18"/>
                        <l>They knowing that this momentary Breath,</l>
                        <l>Doth but detaine them in a Life inſtable</l>
                        <l>Which having once forſaken, they are ſure,</l>
                        <l>T'injoy a Life that ever ſhall endure.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="13">
                        <head>13.</head>
                        <l>Yea to both Good, and Bad <hi>Memento mori,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>is a moſt profitable Document</l>
                        <l>In all Diſcourſe, and Concourſe 'tis a ſtory</l>
                        <l>Fit to bee told, and heard, for moſt are bent</l>
                        <l>Vnto forgetfulneſſe; Nay, many ſtrive,</l>
                        <l>The memory of Death away to drive.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="14">
                        <head>14.</head>
                        <l>Tell a young Royſter, of his vicious wayes,</l>
                        <l>And bid him mend his life, (which is but ſhort)</l>
                        <l>With a faſtidious piſh, hee ſmiles and ſayes</l>
                        <l>Forty yeares hence is time ſufficient for't,</l>
                        <l>And yet too many of theſe Youngſters come,</l>
                        <l>By vnexpected Death, to their long Home.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23901:18"/>
                     <lg n="15">
                        <head>15.</head>
                        <l>Your Female Painters that will mend by Art</l>
                        <l>Natures defects, (to compaſſe baſe deſire)</l>
                        <l>Aske any one of them when ſhee'le depart</l>
                        <l>From folly, and doe what our Lord require;</l>
                        <l>Shee'le ſay that when ſhee's Old all ſhall be left,</l>
                        <l>Some times next Day, ſhe is of Life bereft.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="16">
                        <head>16.</head>
                        <l>Your Goatiſh-Leacher, counſell him to leave</l>
                        <l>Thoſe ſordid courſes wherein hee delights</l>
                        <l>Noe other anſwer you'le from him receive,</l>
                        <l>But, why ſhould I rob Nature of her rights;</l>
                        <l>He'le leave when hee's vnable more to ſinne,</l>
                        <l>Nor Death, nor Iudgement, hee regards a pinne.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="17">
                        <head>17.</head>
                        <l>The Gormandizing-Glutton that deſtroyes,</l>
                        <l>More at one meale, then 20. poore would ſerve</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:23901:19"/>
                        <l>If you demand why hee all this enjoyes</l>
                        <l>While nak'd, and hungry <hi>Christ</hi> i'th ſtreets doth ſtarve</l>
                        <l>He puts off Charity, till Death arreſts him,</l>
                        <l>Till then he thinkes not on't nor him that bleſt him.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="18">
                        <head>18.</head>
                        <l>The bold Blaſphemer (who audaciouſly)</l>
                        <l>Belcheth out Oathes, and Imprecations ſtrange</l>
                        <l>Deviſing new for Curioſity,</l>
                        <l>As men their faſhions, they their oaths do change:</l>
                        <l>Thinke you? if they of Death or Iudgement thought</l>
                        <l>Such damned words could from their mouths be brought.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="19">
                        <head>19.</head>
                        <l>The Grinding Vſurers, the hard Oppreſſors,</l>
                        <l>Did theſe each minute thinke vpon that Day,</l>
                        <l>That ſhall to Iudgement ſummon all tranſgreſſors,</l>
                        <l>Sure conſcience in their ſoules would beare more ſway</l>
                        <l>But Sathan ſtill to traine them in his path</l>
                        <l>Makes them to put farre off the day of Wrath.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23901:19"/>
                     <lg n="20">
                        <head>20.</head>
                        <l>Thoſe Luke-warme Chriſtians, that doe at this day</l>
                        <l>(For worldly Honors and promotions ſake)</l>
                        <l>With Heretiques participate; they'le ſay</l>
                        <l>Before they dye another courſe they'le take,</l>
                        <l>But God in Iudgement oftentimes prevents,</l>
                        <l>And by Deaths warrant fruſtrates their intents.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="21">
                        <head>21.</head>
                        <l>It is a dangerous thing with God to dally,</l>
                        <l>(Whoſe eyes are open to diſcerne all Hearts,)</l>
                        <l>Art thou well minded: ſtand not ſhall I, ſhall I,</l>
                        <l>Take hold of him, whilſt he his Grace imparts,</l>
                        <l>Experience lamentable proves too well,</l>
                        <l>That millions for this fault now burne in Hell.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="22">
                        <head>22.</head>
                        <l>To puniſh our remiſſe and careleſſe Lives,</l>
                        <l>Our Lord hath ſent his Angell with commiſſion</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:23901:20"/>
                        <l>To take from wives their men, from men their wives</l>
                        <l>In many Families is this Diviſion</l>
                        <l>It'h Morne all ſound, at Night all Dead and gone;</l>
                        <l>O, is not this a caſe fit to bemoane.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="23">
                        <head>23.</head>
                        <l>If it be requiſite at any ſeaſon,</l>
                        <l>To thinke of Death, and judgement certainly</l>
                        <l>T'th time of Plague and Peſtilence moſt reaſon</l>
                        <l>Wee have to looke each day and houre to dye;</l>
                        <l>Woefull effects envite vs to this care,</l>
                        <l>Many are ſeized by Death ere the'yr aware.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="24">
                        <head>24.</head>
                        <l>Let every CHRSTIAN thus Expoſtulate,</l>
                        <l>With his own conſcience every houre, and minute,</l>
                        <l>Is my ſtate better then my Neighbours ſtate,</l>
                        <l>(My friends, and Kindred, who have ſuffered int)</l>
                        <l>What priviledge can I vile wretch pretend,</l>
                        <l>That heaven (more then they) ſhould mee defend.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23901:20"/>
                     <lg n="25">
                        <head>25.</head>
                        <l>And if thou bee protected from the ſame</l>
                        <l>Vaunt not thy ſelfe as though thy Merrits were</l>
                        <l>(Without Gods grace) the cauſe: No rather claime</l>
                        <l>Continuance of his love with trembling feare,</l>
                        <l>Glorifie him, and ſtill in this confide</l>
                        <l>That thouſands better then thy ſelfe have dyed</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="26">
                        <head>26.</head>
                        <l>This meeke acknowledgment of Heavenly ayde</l>
                        <l>And thy vnworthineſſe aſſure thy ſelfe</l>
                        <l>Is the beſt Antidote that can be made</l>
                        <l>Againſt the Plague, theſe will not waſt thy pelfe;</l>
                        <l>Not that I ſpeak 'gainſt Corporall proviſion,</l>
                        <l>For th'holy Ghoſt ſayes, honor the Phyſitian.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="27">
                        <head>27.</head>
                        <l>Art thou infected, be not heavy hearted,</l>
                        <l>But with alacrity thy ſelfe prepare</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:23901:21"/>
                        <l>To take from him who hath much Good imparted,</l>
                        <l>This little Ill, now't fals vnto thy ſhare;</l>
                        <l>In holy <hi>Iob</hi> a perfect mirror ſee</l>
                        <l>God plagued him, yet he loved him, why not thee?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="28">
                        <head>28.</head>
                        <l>And thou that with no Sickneſſe art perplext,</l>
                        <l>Bee Charitable vnto all that need,</l>
                        <l>Thinke every houre thy turne may be the next,</l>
                        <l>Prepare for that while yet thy ſelfe art freed:</l>
                        <l>Doe good to all (as holy Scripture ſayth)</l>
                        <l>And chiefly to the Family of Fayth.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="29">
                        <head>29.</head>
                        <l>Bee converſant in Prayer and vſe the meanes</l>
                        <l>As God by meanes of Holy Church affords,</l>
                        <l>That when this ſad Contagion thee reſtraines,</l>
                        <l>Thou being in heart reſolu'd to bee our Lords:</l>
                        <l>While all thy thoughts are in this order kept</l>
                        <l>Our Lord the will, will for the deed accept,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23901:21"/>
                     <lg n="30">
                        <head>30.</head>
                        <l>Aboue all things have care to keepe thy Soule</l>
                        <l>From the contagious malady of Sin,</l>
                        <l>While that beſt part's preſeru'd from being foule</l>
                        <l>Then what eſtate ſo e're thy corpes bee in,</l>
                        <l>Sickneſſe and health, what 'tis the ſender pleaſe</l>
                        <l>Thou ſhalt at all aſſayes finde Ghoſtly eaſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="31">
                        <head>31.</head>
                        <l>Laſtly in generall, all you who bee</l>
                        <l>(Becauſe of this peſtiferous Infection)</l>
                        <l>Sequeſtred and ſhut vp from Company,</l>
                        <l>Bee pleaſed herein to follow my direction:</l>
                        <l>Let this ſecluſion make you thinke what 'tis</l>
                        <l>The glorious Company aboue to miſle.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="32">
                        <head>32.</head>
                        <l>And from this meditation may proceed</l>
                        <l>An ardent fervor of their interceſſion,</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:23901:22"/>
                        <l>Deſire their prayers and merits in your need,</l>
                        <l>That CHRIST of bliſſe may give you full poſſeſſion;</l>
                        <l>And let your memory evermore retaine</l>
                        <l>The thought of Death and Iudgment, joy and paine.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="33">
                        <head>33.</head>
                        <l>Thus for their ſakes who may want better meanes</l>
                        <l>I ſpend this Humble talent with goodwill,</l>
                        <l>Deſiring nothing of them for my paines,</l>
                        <l>But that in their Devotions they may ſtill</l>
                        <l>Remember mee as I for them are zealous,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Sweet</hi> IHESVS <hi>both in Soule and Body heale vs.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <closer>AMEN.</closer>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23901:22"/>
                  <head>A BRIEFE YET DEVOVT PRAYER TO THE GLORIOVS Citizens of the Coeleſtiall IERV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SALEM, <hi>very fit to bee vſed in time of Mortality.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>O! all you Coeleſtiall Inhabitants of the new IERVSALEM, Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whoſe names and memories our pariſh Churches were (by our pious
<pb facs="tcp:23901:23"/>progenitors) Erected, Dedicated and Conſecrated; Wee devoutly begge of you by that vnbounded love where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with our common Lord hath loved you, that you will make Interceſſion vnto him in the behalfe of thoſe pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes whoſe Churches yet reteyne your names; That our mercifull Lord will be pleaſed to revoke the deſtroying Angell lately ſent out with Commiſſion to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh our ſinnes with the Plague of Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; And although (ſuch is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe of theſe times) moſt of the Inhabitants being miſerably conſopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp; inebriated with hereſie, doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne
<pb facs="tcp:23901:23"/>your ſuffrages, and ſeeke (as farre as they are able) vtterly to annihilate that Authority wherewith the King of all Kings hath ennobled you. Yet O yee holy company be pleaſed for their ſakes who devoutly craue your patronage protections, merits and Interceſſions, to deſire our Lord to be mercifull to all in generall, and that he will not for the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie of the Diſobedient puniſh the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient; But rather in mercy ſpare the chaffe for love of the wheate, leaſt pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vp the one hee deſtroy the other, before the harveſt of ſeparation is come. Pray for vs O yee beloved of God, heare
<pb facs="tcp:23901:24"/>vs O mercifull IESVS, and divert thine anger from vs miſerable wretches, who meekely come vnto thee, relying vpon thy wonted favours; O bee pittifull, ſpare vs O benigne IHESV: To whom with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, Bee all glory for ever and ever,</p>
                  <closer>AMEN.</closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
